בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
we are starting today's דף Daf ז, Zayin, we pick up at
the bottom of ו עמוד ב Vav Amud Beit
and we are discussing a very critical issue for הלכה למעשה, Halacha
l'maaseh, which is how can you allow for an עירוב Eruv to
be made? An עירוב Eruv again is the joining together in the
loaf of bread, but that becomes the verb מערבין, Me'arvin, which leads
to why in fact we call the whole creating of the walls
an עירוב. Eruv. So how can you allow for an עירוב Eruv
to be made by the making of walls in a רשות הרבים
Reshus harabim or in other types of streets, מבוי מפולש. Mevoi mefulash.
So the גמרא Gemara basically has said that in a real רשות
הרבים, Reshus harabim, it's pretty impossible unless you're in a walled city.
You need that the door, the entrance and exit of the רשות
הרבים, Reshus harabim, you know, is has doors and the doors are
closed during the day. I mean at one point, the גמרא Gemara
says בירושלים B'Yerushalayim the fact that the gates were closed at night.
So there's a question exactly does it have to be literally every
day or whatnot, but definitely there needs to be doors at the
end and closed, so you can understand why it would be very
difficult to make an עירוב Eruv around a real רשות הרבים. Reshus
harabim. However, what the גמרא Gemara instead did turn to focus is
what about the מבואות המפולשים לרשות הרבים, Meva'os hamefulashim l'reshut harabim, which
are basically the side streets, the
alleys, that the cross-streets of the major arteries that empty into the
רשות הרבים. Reshus harabim. And there the גמרא Gemara had a debate
whether for one of the ends where it connects to רשות הרבים,
Reshus harabim, you would need either a צורת הפתח, Tzurat hapetach, which
is
תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma position, or according to חנניה's Chananya understanding according
to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you'd need actually a door. Not that
the door would have to be closed, it might have the ability
to be closed, but either צורת הפתח Tzurat hapetach or a door.
What we're going to see today is number one a question about
how we rule, and number two also a question about what about
if you have streets that don't even enter into רשות הרבים Reshus
harabim or don't enter into רשות הרבים Reshus harabim at both ends,
only at one end, and maybe that even requires even less. And
that's going to be really what's what is very relevant for us
because since we're working with the assumption based on what we saw
yesterday, רש״י, Rashi, and I mentioned the גאונים, Geonim, that you need
600,000 people to make it a רשות הרבים, Reshus harabim, 600,000 people
using the street. So nowadays we don't have any real רשות הרבים,
Reshus harabim, then the requirement might even be less. But now we're
assuming you have a street entering רשות הרבים Reshus harabim and the
question is whether you need צורת הפתח Tzurat hapetach or do you
need a door. Okay, and so we're first going to see what
the conclusion is with that, and then turn to questions about when
it's even without a רשות הרבים, Reshus harabim, which could allow for
even less than that. Charlie, you had a question?
Oh, I'll ask it later.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay, yes, very quickly, go for it.
Did you say it's just the 600,000 people going in the street,
can it also be like a public gathering place? Is that the
same thing, the 600,000 people daily, or?
Yeah, again, these there's debate about all of those, because it's not
in the גמרא, Gemara, I mean it is in the גמרא, Gemara,
I'm sure the details would not be fully fleshed out, but there
are debates about all of those issues. Yeah.
Did they have a רשות הרבים? Reshus harabim?
Yeah, so that's of course the irony. The irony is nowadays we
don't have רשות הרבים, Reshus harabim, nowadays our cities have only what
a million people in them, we don't have רשות הרבים, Reshus harabim,
of course in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, when they were
discussing it, then they had a רשות הרבים. Reshus harabim. Yeah, I
know, that's quite ironic. Okay, let's move on. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
ההוא מבוי עקום, Hahu mavoi akum, four lines before the lines get
wide, last word on the
line on ו עמוד ב. Vav amud bet. ההוא מבוי עקום, Hahu
mavoi akum, so there was a certain bent מבוי, Mavoi, which is
the way רש״י Rashi explains it. He really only explains it this
way because the גמרא Gemara uses the plural. Oh my gosh, we
have all this writing on the board.
Okay, look
what this looks like,
looks like high school math. Anyway, you have a bent מבוי. Mavoi.
So remember here, you have this, I'll just do it this way,
a little different from רש״י Rashi to make it easier to understand.
So this is your רשות הרבים, Reshus harabim, this is your רשות
הרבים, Reshus harabim, these are your major arteries, right?
Okay, add this to you, this could be Broadway and this could
be, you know, the FDR,
okay. Anyway, these are your רשות הרבים Reshus harabim and these are
the side, the cross-streets, okay? So there's a nice little there's a
nice little shortcut if you want. So this is the מבוי Mavoi
which is מפולש Mefulash because both ends open into רשות הרבים. Reshus
harabim. Okay, remember that yesterday? And there's a question whether it's looked
at as two dead-end מבואות Mavo'os or whether it's looked like it
goes straight into רשות הרבים Reshus harabim and whether you need to
do something over here, you know, whether you need like a צורת
הפתח Tzurat hapetach here or something in order to close it off.
That was a debate that רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. So let's
take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
ההוא מבוי עקום, Hahu mavoi akum, there was a bent מבוי, Mavoi,
דהוה בנהרדעא, De-hava be-Nahardea, that was in נהרדעא. Nahardea. רמיו עליה חומרי
דרב וחומרי דשמואל, Ramyu alei chumrei de-Rav ve-chumrei de-Shmuel, they applied both
the stringencies of רב Rav and the stringencies of
שמואל. Shmuel. of course right, and they mandated doors. Now what does
it mean both stringencies?
חומרי דרב דאמר תורתו כמפולש. Chumrei de-Rav d'amar torato kemufalash. רב Rav
says that this, right, the classic מבוי מפולש maboi mufalash
is when you have your two רשות הרביםs Reshut HaRabim here,
you have Broadway and Central Park West, okay, and then you have
this street that crosses into it, okay, that'll be 96th street. Okay.
So, alright, so that's your מבוי מפולש, maboi mufalash, right, both ends
open into a רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, that is what we've been
talking about where at one end you need a לחי lechi and
at the other end you even need a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
or a door, that's the debate. Right, that's what we debated yesterday,
that debate about what you need by a מבוי מפולש. maboi mufalash.
Then we have this which is debated do you consider it to
be a מבוי מפולש maboi mufalash or not. And that was the
debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel because it doesn't go straight
into רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim it only goes into רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabim another רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim by bending. Those were the two
debates we had yesterday. You're looking very like very uncertain.
Well, I still don't understand why at least on this case on
the right it's not really part of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim.
I mean, it's a different street. It doesn't go it's not the
same flow of traffic as the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. It is,
when it is not cut off from the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim
it is it is considered a רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. But because
its status is because it's connected to the רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim,
okay maybe 96th street is too big of a is not a
good example because you're thinking that that itself should be a רשות
הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, so make it 92nd street. Okay, anyway, the point
is it's a רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim because it's connected but if
you cut off its connection then it stops being a רשות הרבים.
Reshut HaRabim. And even if you virtually cut it off with like
a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach or a door.
So is there any debate about whether or not you need a
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach on both sides or whether or not...
No, because once you have one side cut off then it's a
dead end it's considered dead end and then you only need to
do a לחי lechi on the other side. Okay, yes.
By definition doesn't a מבוי maboi need to have חצרות chatzerot opening
onto it?
Yes, yes to allow for carrying. Right, so this isn't the perfect
example obviously. Okay, so now the גמרא... Gemara...
Isn't that the בית שמאי Beit Shammai בית הלל Beit Hillel case
that was...
Yeah, but we're saying according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so they required doors. Now
how by applying two חומרות? chumrot? How did they require doors by
applying two חומרות? chumrot? חומרי דרב דאמר תורתו כמפולש. Chumrei de-Rav d'amar
torato kemufalash.
So first here was the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
And רב Rav said we treat this as going straight through even
though it has to get there by bending because both ends open
we treat this like straight through. That's the חומרה chumra of רב.
Rav. והאמר רב הלכה כתניא קמא. Ve-ha-amar Rav halacha ke-Tanya Kama.
But one minute, even if you have a straight through מבוי, maboi,
what do you need here? So רב Rav says all you need
is a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, right? The תניא קמא Tanya Kama
said that all you need at this end is a צורת הפתח
tzurat hapetach and רב Rav ruled like that way. The one who
said door was חנניה Hananya and that was שמואל's Shmuel position. So
here we have a funny thing. רב Rav says you have to
treat this bent one like a straight one, but even in the
case of a straight one רב Rav says we rule like the
תניא קמא Tanya Kama that says only a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
is required. So why'd they require a door? So it says והאמר
רב... ve-ha-amar Rav... והאמר רב הלכה
כתניא קמא. ve-ha-amar Rav halacha ke-Tanya Kama. Alright, so they also stick
to שמואל Shmuel דאמר הלכה כחנניה. d'amar halacha ke-Hananya. They were strict
like שמואל Shmuel who says in the straight case you need a
door. One minute. והאמר שמואל תורתו כסתום. Ve-ha-amar Shmuel torato kesatum. But
שמואל Shmuel says that this bent case is considered like its dead
end. So according to שמואל Shmuel you also shouldn't need a door
because שמואל Shmuel would say it's considered dead end, it's not considered
straight.
Okay, כרב דאמר תורתו כמפולש.
ke-Rav d'amar
torato kemufalash.
So then fine so we adopted the stringency of רב Rav that
treated it like it was straight and we adopted the stringency of
שמואל Shmuel that demanded a door. Now the irony is neither רב
Rav nor שמואל Shmuel if you asked them individually would have required
a door. רב Rav would have said oh it's considered like it's
straight and therefore a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is enough because that's
all I demand. שמואל Shmuel would have said oh it's considered dead
end so you don't need a door at all you may not
even a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach maybe a לחי lechi is enough.
They take all the חומרות. chumrot. So neither רב Rav nor שמואל
Shmuel personally would have said you needed a door but the two
debates are not interdependent, right, there's no logical connection between those two
questions and therefore they said we're going to rule the stringent approach
here to treat it like this and the stringent approach here to
demand a door. And this leads the גמרא Gemara into a fascinating
little discussion about the approach of adopting always מחמיר machmir positions. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ומי עבדינן כתרי חומרי, u-mi avdinan ke-trei chumrei, do we really do
like תרי חומרות, trei chumrot, you know meaning two חומרות chumrot of...
now תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean often like you know
there are different debates and we פוסקים לחומרה poskin le-chumra in each
debate. But here the problem is as I just said that neither
רב Rav nor שמואל Shmuel personally would have ever come to this
conclusion. So do we really adopt two חומרות chumrot that never would
have been the position of either side?
Okay. והתניא, Ve-ha tanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא? brayta? לעולם
הלכה כבית הלל, Le-olam halacha ke-veit Hillel,
the ruling is always like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. והרוצה לעשות כדברי
בית שמאי עושה, Ve-ha rotzeh la-asot ke-divrei Beit Shammai ose, but if
you want to go like בית שמאי Beit Shammai you can do,
כדברי בית הלל עושה, ke-divrei Beit Hillel ose, you can do like
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Now that's a contradiction of saying we rule
like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, which the גמרא Gemara will get to
in a minute. But here's our interest right now: assuming that you
had a choice to go like בית שמאי Beit Shammai or בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, that's fine, you can choose one approach. But
מקולי בית שמאי ומקולי בית הלל, mi-kulei Beit Shammai u-mi-kulei Beit Hillel,
if you cherry-pick—now you could cherry-pick either way—if you specifically, you know,
pick always the קולות kulot of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and always
the קולות kulot of בית הלל, Beit Hillel, רשע, rasha, you're considered
a wicked because you're not really submitting to any particular position, you're
just, you're just, you know, קולא kula shopping.
The גמרא Gemara has a nice little דרשה drasha on that in
another place. It says, ועמי מקלו יגיד לו, ve-ami maklo yagid lo,
talking about like necromancy or whatever, you know, witchcraft, "my people will
like their staff will tell them", like you know they do like
magic with their staffs, מקלו יגיד לו, כל המקל יגיד לו. maklo
yagid lo, kol ha-meikel yagid lo. So anyway, so if you only,
if you shop around for
קולות, kulot, רשע. rasha. מחומרי בית שמאי ומחומרי בית הלל, mi-chumrei Beit
Shammai u-mi-chumrei Beit Hillel, on the other hand, if you're always looking
for חומרות chumrot and you adopt everybody's חומרות, chumrot, then עליו הכתוב
אומר, alav ha-katuv omer, regarding such a person the verse says, הכסיל
בחושך הולך, ha-ksil ba-choshech holech, the fool that goes—that gropes around in
the darkness. You know, you don't know what to do. You know,
if you don't know, if you're ignorant, then you're just מחמיר machmir
all the time. So פוסקין, paskin, make a
decision. אי כבית שמאי כקוליהם וכחומריהם, אי כבית הלל כקוליהם וכחומריהם. ei
ke-Beit Shammai ke-kuleihem u-che-chumreihem, ei ke-Beit Hillel ke-kuleihem u-che-chumreihem. Either go like
בית שמאי Beit Shammai for all positions or like בית הלל Beit
Hillel for all positions. So what? Well, that's going to be the
question: why are we saying that you can go like בית שמאי?
Beit Shammai? So first we're going to clarify that before we get
back to our point. הגופא קשיא, Ha gufa kashya, this is internally
a contradiction.
אמרת לעולם הלכה כדברי בית הלל, Amarta le-olam halacha ke-divrei Beit Hillel,
first you said we rule like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. והדר אמרת,
Ve-hadar amarta, and then you said, הרוצה לעשות כדברי בית שמאי עושה,
ha-rotzeh la-asot ke-divrei Beit Shammai ose, that you have the option of
going like בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo
kashya, that's not difficult. כאן קודם בת קול, כאן לאחר בת קול.
Kan kodem bat kol, kan le-achar bat kol. So now we're alluding
to a story which, interestingly, we're going to tell in a few
דפים, dapim, which is going to be a lot of fun. The
story of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai where
they were debating: who do you פוסקין paskin like? Because on the
one hand, בית הלל Beit Hillel was the majority of numbers, but
בית שמאי Beit Shammai were—were acknowledged to be smarter. So do you
go, you know, who do you rule by? The majority—you know, is
it—is it like the popular vote, as it were? Not totally popular,
of course. Or do you go by the people who you think
are, you know, are more, you know, have—are more intelligent, more informed?
So a בת קול bat kol came out and said that we
rule like
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. הלכה כבית הלל. halacha ke-Beit Hillel. אלו ואלו
דברי אלוקים חיים, והלכה כבית הלל. Eilu ve-eilu divrei Elokim chayim, ve-halacha
ke-Beit Hillel. Okay, so that's a famous story. So it says, so
but there was a period where we didn't have that בת קול.
bat kol. And since we didn't have that בת קול, bat kol,
each side could claim that the הלכה halacha should be like them,
either because they had the numbers or because they were the smarter
group. So therefore, the—the second part of this ברייתא brayta that says
you could go like either side was before the בת קול. bat
kol. The first part that says הלכה כבית הלל halacha ke-Beit Hillel
was after it was decided that we always rule like בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. Okay, ואי בעית אימא, ve-i ba'it eima, and if you
want I'll tell you, הא והא לאחר בת קול, ha ve-ha le-achar
bat kol, they could both be after the בת קול. bat kol.
And nevertheless, רבי יהושע הוא דלא משגח בבת קול. Rabbi Yehoshua hu
de-lo mashgach be-bat kol.
It's רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that does not rely on a בת
קול. bat kol. You might remember that story which is that, you
know, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua had one ruling about the תנור של
עכנאי, tannur shel achnai, you have—this particular oven, and all the sages
were against him and he said, if I'm right, you know, let
the—let the—let the river
flow backwards, let the walls of בית מדרש Beit Midrash bend in,
let a heavenly voice come out. And a heavenly voice comes out
and says, you know, רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua right—and then all the
rabbis said, לא בשמים היא. lo va-shamayim hi. You know, God keep
out of it, it's not your decision, it's our decision. So that
idea that, you know, לא משגיחין, lo mashgichin, we don't listen to
a בת קול. bat kol. So the גמרא Gemara says, ah, but
you see רבי יהושע—I'm Rabbi Yehoshua sorry, it wasn't רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua that had the position, it was רבי אליעזר—I Rabbi Eliezer knew
I was saying it wrong. It's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that had
the position, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua got up and said, and
said we don't listen to a בת קול. bat kol. Right, so
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer made all the things happen, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua got up after the heavenly voice came out and said we
don't listen to a בת קול. bat kol. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so maybe according to him, even after the voice came out
for בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, we would
still have it open to rule like בית שמאי Beit Shammai because
we never go by a בת קול. bat kol. Now תוספות Tosafot
asks the question. תוספות Tosafot says, one minute. On the one hand
we say like that גמרא Gemara in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, right?
We say לא בשמים היא lo va-shamayim hi and a בת קול
bat kol does not have any voice, you know, in הלכתי halachic
debate. It all goes by how we down here decide. On the
other hand, he says, we do rule like the בת קול bat
kol of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So
how do we do that? So he says there's an obvious difference.
On the one—and in the case where everybody was against רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, we already had the procedures in place. We knew you
go by a majority vote, and therefore the בת קול bat kol
was coming to contravene what we knew the process of הלכה halacha
was, which is that you had—take a vote, we had a majority
vote and so on. By the
בית הלל-בית שמאי. So if we didn't know which would be the
right process, that case we had to go by the בת קול,
bas kol, but never but never in הלכה halakha once we know
the process do we go by the בת קול. bas kol. So
that anyway but interestingly the גמרא Gemara is positioning it that since
nevertheless to oppose רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua got
up and made an absolute statement, we never listen to a בת
קול, bas kol, maybe he would have said that even by בית
הלל ובית שמאי. Beis Hillel v'Beis Shammai, So maybe for him it's
even still an open possibility to rule like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
Anyway ואיבעית אימא הכי קאמר. v'iybayis ayma hachi ka'amar. Okay. So if
you want you could say so ואיבעית אימא הכי קאמר, v'iybayis ayma
hachi ka'amar, כל היכא דמשכחת תרי
תנאי ותרי אמוראי kol heicha
d'mishkachas trei tannai v'trei amorai
or here's how you could read it. Yes clearly we do always
rule like בית הלל, Beit Hillel this was all talking לאחר בת
קול, l'achar bas kol, nobody disagrees that we rule like בית הלל,
Beis Hillel but here's what it was saying. Anytime you find similar
debate to that of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beis Hillel v'Beis Shammai,
either two תנאים tannaim debating or אמוראים amoraim debating דפליגי אהדדי d'paligi
ahadadi that they argue with one another כעין מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית
הלל k'ein machlokes Beis Shammai v'Beis Hillel similar to this type of
a debate, you have two schools that are arguing about a lot
of things and it's in an analogous situation, לא ליהוי כקולי דמר
וכקולי דמר, lo l'avei k'kulei d'mar v'k'kulei d'mar, you cannot all pick
the קולות kulos of each school ולא כחומרי דמר וכחומרי דמר v'lo
k'chumrei d'mar v'k'chumrei d'mar
and not like the חומרות chumras of each school אלא אי כקולי
דמר כחומרי עביד ela ee k'kulei d'mar k'chumrei avid
either you do all the קולות kulos and all the חומרות chumras
או כקולי דמר כחומרי עביד o k'kulei d'mar k'chumrei avid or the
other position, all the קולות kulos and all the חומרות. chumras. So
first of all we have an interesting digression as I said which
we're going to see more of, which is this question about this
בת קול bas kol of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beis Hillel u'Beis
Shammai, but basically in a ברייתא Baraisa that seems to indicate that
it's possible to rule like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai. so how do
we understand that ברייתא? Baraisa? So three possibilities, either that was before
the בת קול bas kol before there was a consensus that we
always go like בית הלל Beis Hillel, or it was even after
but it was this position of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who argued
on רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the בית מדרש beis medrash with
the בת קול bas kol and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says we
always we always reject בת קול bas kol so according to רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua maybe you could still פסקן pasken like בית שמאי
Beis Shammai, or that it talks about analogous
analogous types of cases. Okay but the point being you have debating
schools, you have to either consistently be adopt one school's position, you
cannot go ahead and קולא kula shop or חומרא chumra shop. Yes
Charlie.
But that בת קול bas kol רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua had an
explicit פסוק pasuk from לא בשמים היא,
Lo bashamayim hee, right.
And nobody argued about that so how can there be any debate?
Well that yeah I mean that's basically תוספות Tosafos's point that that
nobody really debated that case because that case we already knew the
process procedure. The question was can you use the בת קול bas
kol when you don't know the procedure? Okay and so on that
please pass me a cup by the way Charlie I need a
water. Yeah.
Why can't why did they feel you always have to rule for
one team and you have to choose a team? Why can't what's
so bad if you find a minority opinion that if you why
not use your own judgment?
So
and sometimes we do that.
the גמרא Gemara is going to say that. Okay so let's take
a look. First of all if you use your own judgment I
think that's an excellent point then you're פסקן, paskening, then you're not
just adopting somebody else's position. You're assessing the information and you're פסקן
paskening right so that then it happens to be that your פסק
psak lines up with different positions that's different than just sort of
adopting who's going to be my רבי, rebbi, who am I going
to go by,
okay, but even within this גמרא Gemara let's see how the גמרא
Gemara now modifies the point. So the גמרא Gemara says מכל מקום
קשיא mikol makom kashya so it's difficult because it seems like you
have to be consistent. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק כולהי כרב
עבדוה. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, kulei k'Rav avduah. You're right they
really did it like רב. Rav. ואמר רב הונא אמר רב V'amar
Rav Huna amar Rav though according to רב Rav even though he
says it's a מפולש mefulash you would really say you could do
enough with the צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. So why did he demand
that you use a door? So because דאמר רב הונא אמר רב
הלכה ואין מורין כן, d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav halakha v'ein morin
kein, even though the הלכה halakha is that a צורת הפתח tzuras
hapesach is enough for these types of מבואות, maboys, you don't go
ahead and פסקן pasken that publicly. Again getting back to a theme
we saw before about questions about whether people will be sloppy. So
therefore רב Rav in practice sort of adopted the position of שמואל
Shmuel that you use door. ולרב אדא בר אבא אמר רב U'leRav
Adda bar Abba amar Rav but one minute not everybody agrees to
that. רב אדא בר אבא Rav Adda bar Abba says in the
name of רב Rav הלכה ומורין כן halakha umorin kein that רב
Rav actually said we do publicize that position and a צורת הפתח
tzuras hapesach is enough. So מאי איכא למימר mai ikka l'meimar we're
back to our question, how is it they adopted the חומרות chumras
of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel and were not consistent? So אמר
רב שיזבי Amar Rav Shizbi so now comes רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi
and says כי לא עבדינן כחומרי דבי תרי ki lo avdinan k'chumrei
d'bei trei when is it we don't go like the חומרות chumras
of two different
positions היכא דסתרי אהדדי heicha d'sasri ahadadi when it's mutually contradictory כגון
שדרה וגולגולת k'gon shidra v'gulgoles like the case of the spine and
the skull. What does that
mean?
דתניא במתניתא d'tana b'matnisa השדרה והגולגולת שחסרו hashidra v'hagulgoles shechasru if you
have a spine or skull that are lacking some part you know
part of their bones or a rib from the. spine. וכמה חיסרון
בשדרה? Vekama chisaron bishiddra? What is considered? Now that is, this is
when you have only the bones, you don't have flesh on it,
and how much causes טומאה ואוהל tumah v'ohel for a dead body
causes the impurity to spread underneath the roof. So it has to
be complete, and if it's not complete, then it doesn't transmit טומאה
tumah under the roof. So what is considered a lacking by the
spine? בית שמאי אומרים שתי חוליות, Beis Shammai omrim shtei chulyos, two
ribs. ובית הלל אומרים חוליה אחת, U'Veis Hillel omrim chulya achas, one
rib. ובגולגולת, U'vegugoles, and when it comes to the skull...
vertebrae, right, right, ribs is front, I'm sorry, vertebrae, thank you. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says two vertebrae and בית הלל Beis Hillel, says
one vertebra. ובגולגולת, U'vegugoles, when it comes to the skull, בית שמאי
אומרים כמלוא מקדח, Beis Shammai omrim kemlo makde'ach, the amount coming out
from like an awl, if you would puncture, you know, whatever the
size of a hole made by an awl is. ובית הלל אומרים
כדי שיינטל מן החי וימות, U'Veis Hillel omrim kedei sheyinnatel min hachai
veyamus, a bigger amount that if you would remove it from a
live person, it would definitely kill it. תוספות Tosafot points out that
even for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai it's based on what would kill
a person, but בית הלל Beis Hillel means a larger size that
would definitely kill a person. Okay, now that's the debate by how
much of that spine or the skull causes טומאה tumah for a
dead body.
But ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, וכן
לעניין טרפה, vechen le'inyan tereifa, the same debate would be if an
animal was missing a vertebra or an animal was missing a piece
of bone in the skull, when would it be considered a טרפה?
tereifa? Because it's the same debate about how much would it lead
to the person dying, how much would it lead to the animal
dying? Okay, so they have an exact debate. Now, notice though, the
position of whether it's a קולא kula or a חומרא chumra reverses
itself. Because if you have a skeleton of a dead person without
the flesh, just the skeleton under roof, so if you adopt בית
הלל's Beis Hillel position, as soon as it's missing one vertebra, okay,
no טומאה. tumah. That's, you know, that's more lenient. But
then you come to the animal that's missing a vertebra, and you
say oh, one vertebra, it's already a טרפה. tereifa. So בית הלל's
Beis Hillel position of one vertebra is a leniency for causing טומאה,
tumah, cause at a lower threshold it'll like at a, you know,
with a low threshold it'll stop causing טומאה tumah under the roof,
but it's also a חומרא chumra for טרפה, tereifa, cause at a
low threshold the animal will be a טרפה. tereifa. So if somebody
basically said, you know, in one case by the dead body, I'm
going to go like בית הלל Beis Hillel and be, I'm sorry,
I'm going to go like בית שמאי Beis Shammai, and be strict
and say it needs two vertebrae, and since it needs to be
lacking two vertebrae, and when it comes to the טרפה, tereifa, I'm
going to go like בית הלל Beis Hillel and be strict and
say only one vertebra, then you are taking the exact same debate
and going opposite ways in opposite cases. And that's considered the idea
that you should not be מחמיר machmir both ways or מקיל meykel
both ways. Yes, Charles.
In general, in determining sizes of שיעורים, shiurim, you're going to create
leniencies and stringencies at the same time. Like for פסח. Pesach.
Right, you're right. So it's not only here, but this was just
a good example of how it could be applied.
As opposed to or what?
Right, as opposed to, let me just say it, okay, אבל היכא
דלא סתרי אהדדי, aval heicha delo sasri ahadadei, when they don't contradict,
עבדינן, avdinan, we do do it. So here, the point is there's
no logical contradiction. It would have been theoretically possible for רב Rav
or שמואל Shmuel to have held it both stringent, held both stringencies.
You could hold a bent thing is like a straight one, and
you could hold that a straight one needs a דור. dor. Those
are not logically two positions that don't fit together. So even though
it happens to be that neither רב Rav nor שמואל Shmuel holds
of both stringent sides, there's no problem of holding of both of
those positions at the same time. Whereas in the case of בית
הלל Beis Hillel ובית שמאי, v'Beis Shammai. the case the גמרא Gemara
gives, the problem of being
מקיל—again, meykel Rivka's point is a good one in general, which is
that if you're פסקנינג, paskening, that's a different issue, but adopting a
position and adopting only the קולא kula positions or only the חומרא
chumra in a way in which contradicts itself, that's a problem. Now,
I should, it should be pointed out that even in the גמרא's
Gemara case, it doesn't contradict itself at the same moment, right? It's
not like in one case you're פסקנינג paskening a contradictory way. When
I have a טרפה tereifa I פסקן pasken one way, and when
I have a dead body in a room, I פסקן pasken another
way. And by the way, that happens all the time, you know,
that פוסקים poskim adopt very often, I mean, depends on the פוסק,
posek, but very often if you look at like
רב משה, Rav Moshe, רב עובדיה יוסף, Rav Ovadia Yosef, who are
פוסקים poskim who try to be very responsive to the human condition
and try to find leniencies when they're appropriate and available, they will
very often in one case rely on certain lenient positions, and then
in another case rely on the other side of the camp because
that works out to be a lenient position in this other case.
And so that's, it's interesting that exactly that actually happens all the
time, even though the גמרא Gemara says it's not supposed to. I
mean, logically it's not a contradiction, right? Because it's a debate and,
you know, and therefore those two cases are not within the same
case itself. That would be, you'd have to figure out a case
in which it would be an internal contradiction within the case itself.
But it is a problem that the גמרא Gemara seems to be
like that you have to, but
I think,
I think that, that
even from different cases. As opposed to
פסקנינג paskening or as opposed to dealing with a question of doubt
how you
פסקן, pasken, to actually actively פסקן, pasken, not to say, "Well, we
don't know, so we'll have to be מחמיר. machmir. Well, we don't
know, it's a debate; in this case, we can rely on this
position." That's sort of like how do you
פסקן pasken without assuming that there's within an area of doubt as
opposed to I think what the גמרא Gemara is saying is more
actively פסקנינג paskening contradictory positions. Okay, but a very interesting גמרא Gemara
about this issue. So the גמרא Gemara has one final case about
that. It says, ומהיכא דסתרי אהדדי לא עבדינן? umeheicha d'sasri ahadadi lo
avdinan? Is it really true that when they contradict themselves we do
not do, we cannot פסקן? pasken? מתיב רב משרשיא, Masiv Rav Mesharshiya,
or רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshiya asks מעשה דרבי עקיבא, maaseh d'Rabbi Akiva,
מעשה דרבי
עקיבא maaseh d'Rabbi Akiva שלקט אתרוג באחד בשבט sheleket esrog b'echad b'shvat
ונהג בה ב' איסורין, v'nahag bah bais issurin, אחד כדברי בית שמאי
ואחד כדברי בית הלל. echad k'divrei Bais Shamai v'echad k'divrei Bais Hillel.
Now there is a question when is ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'shvat, when
is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for the trees? So for us that
means when do we have a nice little סדר Seder and have
some something some Jewish holiday that relates to the agriculture or the
environment. But for the גמרא Gemara what it meant was when you
take fruit from trees, which שמיטה, Shmita, which year does it go
by in the שמיטה Shmita cycle? So if you pick a tree,
a stem from before ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'shvat, it goes from the
previous year. If you pick it after ט"ו בשבט Tu B'shvat it
goes from the following year. The relevance would be let's say to
a שמיטה Shmita year itself, or let's say it's between the second
and the third year of the cycle. In the second year you
give מעשר שני maaser sheni and in the third year you give
מעשר עני. maaser ani. So which do you give? So it depends
if you pick the tree for the apple or whatever you're picking
before or after ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'shvat. Now that's what בית הלל
Beis Hillel says. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says before or after is
it ראש חודש שבט? Rosh Chodesh Shvat? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
picked an אתרוג esrog between ראש חודש שבט Rosh Chodesh Shvat and
ט"ו בשבט Tu B'shvat and he gave מעשר maaser twice, מעשר עני
maaser ani and מעשר שני, maaser sheni, even though you can never
give מעשר עני maaser ani and מעשר שני maaser sheni in the
same year because he was פסקנינג paskening like the חומרות chumras of
both positions. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says אחד כדברי בית
שמאי ואחד כדברי בית הלל.
echad k'divrei Bais Shamai v'echad
k'divrei Bais Hillel. So how could you do that? That's contradictory, obviously
they both can't be true. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי עקיבא
גמרא אסתפקא ליה Rabbi Akiva gemara istapkiah lay and this might tie
into the point we were making before. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva did
not know what the tradition was ולא ידע אי בית הלל בחד
בשבט אמור אי בחמישה עשר בשבט אמור, v'lo yada ei Bais Hillel
b'chad b'shvat amur ei b'chamesha asar b'shvat amur, ועבד הכא לחומרא והכא
לחומרא. v'avad haka l'chumra v'haka l'chumra. He's not פסקנינג paskening both בית
הלל Bais Hillel and בית שמאי. Bais Shamai He does not know
what the position of בית הלל Bais Hillel is. Does בית הלל
Bais Hillel say ראש חודש שבט Rosh Chodesh Shvat or does he
say ט"ו בשבט? Tu B'shvat? So since he didn't know what בית
הלל Bais Hillel said therefore he had no choice but to be
מחמיר machmir both ways. So this gets back to the point that
we were in yeah gets back to the point that we were
discussing before about that really
the אם פסק, im psak, you will often find somebody will say
in this case I'll go this way, in this case I'll go
that way, and here by the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara you
see that if it's done out of a sense of ספק safek
what the position is that you have maybe more latitude. But to
actually actively פסקן pasken a position and then in another case actively
פסקן pasken the other side, not just to say we don't know
so we can rely on, say we rule like this position, right?
We rule that שבת Shabbos is defined by רבינו תם צאת הכוכבים,
Rabbeinu Tam tzeis hakochavim, and then another case they say we rule
like the הגר"א ha-Gra that it's based on not 72 minutes, we
rule like the הגר"א ha-Gra it's based on 13 minutes or whatever
it is, and I actively say we rule that way, so that
I can't do in different even in different cases. But if you
have a case of a doubt how to rule that gives you
more latitude to either be מחמיר machmir both ways or as some
פוסקים poskim do to be מיקל meikel both ways when the situation
warrants. Yes.
So here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is trying to avoid being טבל
tevel which is a very serious sin and sometimes today we will
be מחמיר machmir in all directions to avoid certain sins or levels
that are of a particular level.
Okay so your point is what?
Well so it so this may not be
when are you מחמיר, machmir, when are you מיקל, meikel,
this may not generalize to ordinary...
right I understand. You know, so it always is question and what
is the degree of need and so on and also very often
just what's the general גישה gisha of the פוסק posek right? So
yes.
And how do you deal with תרתי דסתרי tartei d'sasri for example,
in other words like, you know,
מנחה Mincha after on שבת Shabbos it's different. I mean like isn't
that contradictory or...
okay I'm not going to deal with זמן מנחה zman Mincha because
the גמרא, Gemara, whatever, that's a very particular case. But anyway can
this challenge be raised sometimes by the way we פסקן? pasken? Yes.
Let's move on. So what have we concluded? We've concluded first of
all that we had a very lovely little digression
about
whether you can פסקן pasken in contradictory ways what we had two
digressions number one... That before the בת קול bas kol came out,
you could rule either like בית שמאי Bais Shamai. or בית הלל,
Bais Hillel and even after the בת קול bas kol came out,
it’s possible to attribute to
ר' יהושע
Rebbe Yehoshua who opposed ר' אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, it’s possible to attribute
the position that even we don’t go even by that בת קול
bas kol and you can still rule like בית שמאי. Beis Shammai
That was one digression. The bigger point of the digression was
that
you cannot adopt positions that are always look for חומרות chumros always
look for קולות, kulos, but the גמרא Gemara actually pulls back on
that and says that’s really only a problem when they are mutually
contradictory. The greatest example that would be mutually contradictory in the same
case. The גמרא Gemara even says just it’s contradictory because you’re פסקנ'ינג
paskening different ways in different cases on the same position. And even
there we saw at the end that that’s more about when you
actually פסקן pasken that way rather than when you do it out
of doubt. So that was one fascinating digression about the whole process
of פסק psak and קולות kulos and חומרות. chumros. More to our
point, how do we rule about this case about a מבוי? mavoi?
Do you need a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach or a door? That
remains a debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and even according
to רב Rav who says צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, he might say
הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. So if that was
really the conclusion that you needed a door, then again we would
be stuck nowadays trying to make an עירוב eiruv in the great
outdoors because who’s putting up doors? So how do we allow for
עירוב eiruv if here even רב Rav might say that הלכה ואין
מורין כן halacha v’ein morin kein and that you need a door?
So that turns us now to the next section of the גמרא.
Gemara.
But the the other position was הלכה ומורין כן. halacha umorin kein.
Right.
יתיב רב יוסף קמיה דרב הונא. Yasiv Rav Yosef kimei deRav Huna.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef was sitting in front of רב הונא.
Rav Huna. ויתיב וקאמר V’yasiv v’ka’amar and sitting and saying, אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said in the name of רב, Rav, מחלוקת בסרטיא מכאן וסרטיא
מכאן. Machlokes besratya mikan usratya mikan. The only debate about whether you
need a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach or a door, this is the
debate of the תנאים, Tannaim, חנניה Chananya versus תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
which is also the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. But
that only debate of whether you need a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach
or a door
is
only if there is a major רשות הרבים reshus harabbim at both
ends of the מבוי. mavoi. Like in my example there, you have
Broadway and Central Park West. That’s when there’s a debate whether you
need a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach or a
door. או פלטיא מכאן ופלטיא מכאן, O platya mikan uplatya mikan, or
both ends open up into a major like square, like into Times
Square on both ends. Okay. אבל סרטיא מכאן וביקעה מכאן, Aval sratya
mikan uvikah mikan,
if at one end it opens up into a major thoroughfare and
then the other side it opens up into a valley, into you
know, so let’s say one street feeds into Central Park itself and
the other end goes into Broadway. So in that case, או ביקעה
מכאן וביקעה מכאן, o vikah mikan uvikah mikan, or on both ends
it opens up into a valley, it doesn’t even open up into
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim at all. So in that case, עושה צורת
הפתח מכאן ולחי וקורה מכאן. oseh tzuras hapesach mikan ulechi vekorah mikan.
Then you can just make a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach on one
side and a לחי lechi or קורה, korah, horizontal or vertical beam
on the other side. And this is basically what allows us to
make an עירוב eiruv because this basically says if one of these
is not a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim nowadays, then everybody would agree
that all you need is a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. And therefore
what we do is we make a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach around
all the streets. So once we say that we don’t have a
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim nowadays, צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach is what suffices.
Okay, so that’s what he says.
So it has to be a כרמלית karmelis on one side.
As long as it’s not a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim on both
sides, צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach suffices. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. השתא סרטיא מכאן וביקעה מכאן עושה לה, Hashta sratya mikan
uvikah mikan oseh lah, I’m sorry, the גמרא Gemara says, השתא סרטיא
מכאן וביקעה מכאן עושה לה צורת הפתח מכאן ולחי וקורה מכאן. Hashta
sratya mikan uvikah mikan oseh lah tzuras hapesach mikan ulechi vekorah mikan.
So if you said that when there’s a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim
on one side and a valley on the other, a צורת הפתח
tzuras hapesach is enough, עושה
לה צורת הפתח מכאן ולחי וקורה מכאן. oseh lah tzuras hapesach mikan
ulechi vekorah mikan. If that’s enough to make a צורת הפתח tzuras
hapesach on one side and לחי lechi and קורה korah the other,
ביקעה מכאן וביקעה מכאן, vikah mikan uvikah mikan, if it opens up
into a valley at both ends, it doesn’t open up into רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim at any end, מיבעיא? mibaya? Is there any question
that a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach would be enough? So why did
you have to give me the second case?
Maybe tell me you wouldn’t have to do anything.
הא הכי קאמר. Ha hachi ka'amar. This is what it means. No,
because you need a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. סרטיא מכאן וביקעה מכאן.
Sratya mikan uvikah mikan. If you have a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim
on one side and a valley on the other, נעשה, na’aseh, that’s
just as equal to ביקעה מכאן וביקעה מכאן vikah mikan uvikah mikan
as if there’s a valley on both ends and therefore you can
have a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach on one side and nobody everyone
agrees you don’t need a door. So this is what we’ve learned
over the last few days is A, the challenge of making an
עירוב, eiruv, because if you have a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
then you would need a door at both ends of the רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim.
Why that’s not a problem nowadays because of the idea of six
hundred thousand, which gets introduced by רש"י Rashi and the גאונים. Geonim.
And B, that if you don’t have a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
what do you need? Not a door, which was being debated, but
everybody would agree that if there’s no רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, all
you need is a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. Right.
Oh, the other position was לחי lechi and the other.
Right. ומסיים בשמיה דרב יהודה *Umisayem Bishmei DeRav Yehuda*. Now, he ended
that statement; first he said in the name of רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda אמר רב Rav *Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, then he had one
coda to the statement which was just in the name of רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*, and he didn't say who רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda* said it in the name of, and here
was the end of the statement: אם היה מבוי mavoi כלה לרחבה
אין צריך כלום *Im Haya Maboi Kala Lerachava Ein Tzarech Klum*. If
the מבוי mavoi. *Maboi* ends up in enters into a רחבה rachavah.
*Rachava*, רחבה rachavah *Rachava* is a backyard, it does not need anything.
So basically what that means is you have one end into
a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *Reshus Harabim*, and the other end, here's
your house,
I don't know if that's the house, okay, here's the house's backyard,
it's a walled backyard, it's a רשות היחיד *Reshus Hayachid*, it's a
רשות היחיד *Reshus Hayachid*, it's a רחבה *Rachava*, it's a walled backyard,
and the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *Reshus Harabim* enters into it. Now,
it says, no, the מבוי mavoi *Maboi*. So you don't need anything
at that end. Now of course you don't need anything at that
end, it's going into a walled place. So רש"י *Rashi* says we
have to assume, although it's not said in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
that there's a break on the other side of the wall here
and it enters into another רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *Reshus Harabim* here.
So even though there's a, you know, the wall of this backyard
broke in two places, so it does open into רשות הרבים reshut
ha-rabim. *Reshus Harabim* in both places, but it's not like it's a
street that goes through. It opens up to my backyard and at
the other end of my backyard there's a break in the wall
and there's another רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim? *Reshus Harabim* there, and even
though that's true, because it ends in here and this is a
walled place, even though there's a break in the opposite end facing
wall, you don't need anything at this side. All you would do
is put a... as put a לחי lechi? *Lechi* or קורה korah
*Kora* on this side.
How's that a רשות היחיד *Reshus Hayachid* then?
It's got four walls. It's got it looks like this, right? If
you have that, that's a רשות היחיד *Reshus Hayachid*, right? Based on
how big those breaks are, whatever. I mean we'll discuss those issues
coming up, but it's still enough of a.
As long as the breaks aren't too big.
Exactly.
And there's a door.
Okay. So let's take a look.
So he says, if it's a מבוי mavoi *Maboi*, רשות היחיד *Reshus
Hayachid*, and another מבוי mavoi, *Maboi*, רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim, *Reshus Harabim*.
Not even another מבוי mavoi *Maboi*, directly רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *Reshus
Harabim*. Look at the picture in רש"י *Rashi*. It empties straight into
רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמר ליה amar leih,
אביי לרב יוסף *Amar Lei Abaye LeRav Yosef*. So אביי *Abaye* said
to רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef*. So this was רב Rav יוסף
*Rav Yosef* was telling this over to רב Rav, הונא *Rav Huna*,
so אביי *Abaye* turned to רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef* and said:
הדין דרב יהודה דשמואל היא *Hadin DeRav Yehuda DeShmuel Hi*. That which
you just said, this last point in the name of רב Rav
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* and you didn't know who it was in the
name of, it's really in the name of שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*. You
see, you didn't think we were going to finish the דף *Daf*
today? Now I know what's on side B.
So רב Rav יהודה *Rav Yehuda* had two... רב Rav יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* would often say statements in the name of רב Rav, *Rav*
and often in the name of שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*. So אביי *Abaye*
is saying this last point, that has to be שמואל's Shmuel. *Shmuel's*
position, it can't be רב's Rav *Rav's* position. Why? אי דרב קשיא
דרב אדרב *Ei DeRav Kashya DeRav ADeRav*, because if it's רב Rav
*Rav*, then רב Rav, *Rav* contradicts himself. איתמר itmar, הכי *Itmar Hachi*
in two ways. דאמר רב Rav. ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב Rav
*DeAmar Rav Yirmiyah Bar Abba Amar Rav*, רב Rav ירמיה בר אבא
*Rav Yirmiyah Bar Abba* says in the name of רב Rav *Rav*:
מבוי mavoi שנפרץ במלואו לחצר *Maboi Shenifratz Bemilo'o Lechatzar*, ונפרצה חצר chatzer
כנגדו
*Venifretza Chatzer Kenegdo*. This is exactly the exact same case, okay? It's
just with a חצר chatzer. *Chatzer* as opposed to רחבה *Rachava*. So
it's exact same case, חצר chatzer. *Chatzer*. So you have a מבוי
mavoi שנפרץ במלואו *Maboi Shenifratz Bemilo'o*, which means,
ignore not related to the other picture.
What it means במלואו *Bemilo'o* is that the entire opening of the
מבוי mavoi *Maboi*, the מבוי mavoi *Maboi* has absolutely no wall. At
the חצר chatzer *Chatzer* it's only a partial opening in the wall
of the חצר chatzer *Chatzer*, right? From the perspective of the חצר
chatzer *Chatzer* it's only a partial opening. From the perspective of the
מבוי mavoi *Maboi* it's a full opening. So it's נפרץ במלואו לחצר
*Nifratz Bemilo'o Lechatzar* and כנגדו לרשות הרבים *Kenegdo Lereshus Harabim*, and then
the חצר chatzer *Chatzer*, right, and there enters opens up right into
the רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*. It's exact, it's exactly the same case,
except with a חצר chatzer *Chatzer* instead of a רחבה *Rachava*. Okay.
So מבוי mavoi שנפרץ במלואו לחצר *Maboi Shenifratz Bemilo'o Lechatzar*, ונפרצה חצר
chatzer. כנגדו *Venifretza Chatzer Kenegdo*, and the חצר chatzer. *Chatzer* is broken
at the opposite end, חצר מותרת muteret, ומבוי אסור assur *Chatzer Muteres
Umaboi Assur*. The חצר *Chatzer* is permissible, you can carry in the
חצר *Chatzer*, but not in the מבוי mavoi *Maboi*. Now, why not
in the מבוי mavoi *Maboi*? Even if for example
this מבוי mavoi *Maboi* was dead-ended here and you had, you know,
and you had other חצרות *Chatzeros* and you wanted to carry in
the מבוי mavoi *Maboi*, so you'd say well what do you want
to do if you want to carry in a מבוי mavoi *Maboi*
like this? So this is the opening of the מבוי *Maboi*, you
know, you put a לחי lechi *Lechi* or something and you carry
in the מבוי *Maboi*, right? So why is the מבוי אסור assur
*Maboi Assur*? So the מבוי *Maboi* is אסור assur, *Assur* because there
are people who live in the חצר *Chatzer*, right, there are houses
around the חצר *Chatzer* and they didn't make an עירוב eruv *Eiruv*
with together with the מבוי *Maboi*, okay? So therefore since this totally
opens up into the חצר *Chatzer* and these people didn't make an
עירוב eruv, *Eiruv*, then they're considered to be commingling with these people
and you can't, if two groups that didn't make an עירוב eruv.
*Eiruv* that are in the same space they didn't make an עירוב
eruv. *Eiruv* together you can't carry in the מבוי *Maboi*. But you
can make an עירוב eruv *Eiruv*, right? What? You can, but it's
saying that you didn't. Okay, now. So that's the point about where
it says מבוי אסור assur. *Maboi Assur*. Why is the חצר מותר
*Chatzer Mutar*? Because from the חצר's *Chatzer's* perspective it's not a full
opening. From the חצר's *Chatzer's* perspective... perspective it's like we don't want
to have anything to do with those מבוי people, you know, we
have that's a little door but you know fundamentally we're blocked off,
you know, we're surrounded, it's not like we're totally exposed to the
מבוי people. So they're not one of us. So therefore from the
חצר's perspective, they don't have to associate with the מבוי. But from
the מבוי's perspective, their entire one side is entirely open up into
the חצר. They are related to the חצר. Okay, so that's an
interesting case about one group's, you know, from one group's perspective and
the other. This is not, this is going to be issues that
will come up later in much greater depth, okay, two groups that
didn't make an עירוב eruv. together. And the idea here is from
the מבוי's perspective, they're commingled with the חצר because their entire wall
is open. From the חצר's perspective, they're not commingled.
Even if the חצר people put up that לחי?
lechi Yeah, it doesn't matter. Okay, so so
the
point is מבוי שנפרץ במלואו לחצר ונפרצה חצר כנגדו חצר מותרת ומבוי
אסור.
mavoi she-nifratz bi-mlo'o le-chatzer ve-nifretzah chatzer
kenegdo chatzer muteret u-mavoi assur. Now, the fact that that what I
just described to you has to do with making the עירוב, eruv
but the point is, the חצר is still מותרת, okay? And now
wait a minute, hold on a second.
Just give me a second.
Right. So the, I'm sorry, the מבוי, so now what I described
to you had to do with the fact of making an עירוב.
eruv I actually jumped ahead, I described to you what the conclusion
is going to be. But initially what he thought was that the
reason the מבוי was אסור had nothing to do with the point
I just made about the עירוב. eruv The reason the מבוי was
אסור was because of the opening at the other end, that the
מבוי was still considered to be connected to the רשות הרבים. That's
what he thought. So he said look, רב says the מבוי is
אסור, obviously it's connected to the רשות הרבים. So how could you
say here רב says that you don't need anything at this end?
Okay, meaning I made it a little too complicated because I jumped
to the answer. But the question was here רב says when it
goes into this and there's a break in the opposite wall, you
don't need to do anything at that end. Here with רב, here
רב said in this case the מבוי is אסור. It's the exact
same case. So we assume it's because it opens up into רשות
הרבים. So you see that can't be רב's position. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר ליה,
he said back to him אנא לא ידענא. ana lo yadana. Look,
I don't know, but עובדא הוה בדורא דרעותא, uvda hava be-Dura di-Re'uta,
there was a case like this in a village of shepherds, מבוי
שכלה לרחבה הוה, mavoi she-kala le-rachavah hava, it was a מבוי that
ended, opens up into a backyard and presumably again not stated in
the גמרא Gemara but presumably that backyard opens into a רשות הרבים.
ואתא לקמיה דרב יהודה ולא אצריכיה ולא מידי, ve-ata le-kamei de-Rav Yehuda
ve-lo itzrichai ve-lo midi, and he said he didn't need anything. So
I do know that רב יהודה said that position. That in that
case you don't need, right, the case here goes into a backyard
with walls, opens the other end, I know he said you don't
need anything. So that I know.
So you're, so you're telling me it can't be רב because of
because רב says this is a problem? I don't know about that.
I know that wasn't a problem, that's what רב יהודה said.
But you don't need a לחי lechi over there what you drew
over there by רשות הרבים?
In that case, right, because it goes into the רחבה. Yeah.
So ואי קשיא משמיה דרב דהוה, ve-i kashya mi-shmeih de-Rav de-hava, so
ואי קשיא משמיה דרב, ve-i kashya mi-shmeih de-Rav, and if you think
that's not consistent with רב, fine, תהוי משמיה דשמואל ולא קשיא מידי.
tehavei mi-shmeih de-Shmuel ve-lo kashya midi.
So so don't give me a hard time. You want it to
be according to שמואל, Shmuel let it be according to שמואל. Shmuel
I just know רב יהודה said it. So you said it couldn't
be in the name of רב because רב says the other case
is a problem. No, so it's not רב, it's שמואל. But I
actually can tell you that it is consistent with רב. Why? Because
השתא דאמר ליה רב ששת לרב שמואל בר אבא ואמרי לה לרב
יוסף בר אבא אסברא לך. hashta de-amar leih Rav Sheshet le-Rav Shmuel
bar Abba ve-amrei lah le-Rav Yosef bar Abba asbera lach. Look, let
me explain to you what's going on here. כאן שערבו וכאן שלא
ערבו. kan she-irvu ve-kan she-lo irvu. The difference is did you make
an עירוב eruv, or not make an עירוב. eruv. דרב אדרב נמי
לא קשיא de-Rav a-de-Rav nami lo kashya so therefore it's not a
problem with רב as well. כאן שערבו בני חצר עם בני מבוי
כאן שלא ערבו. kan she-irvu bnei chatzer im bnei mavoi kan she-lo
irvu. Okay, when if you've made an עירוב eruv together, right, the
people here in the רחבה they're like they got two houses that
opened up, whatever, if they made an עירוב together, then it's fine.
From the perspective of walls you don't need anything. From the perspective
of the עירוב you're okay. In this case, it's true, you don't
need anything from the perspective of walls at this end. But because
there's no עירוב, that's why you have the problem. That the חצר
is okay because the מבוי is not part of it. But the
מבוי is no good because it is connected to the חצר. That's
what I explained to you before and the problem here is not
the lack of walls, the problem here is the lack of עירוב.
Okay, so with that we have come to the conclusion that the
big issue in terms of the walls is that nowadays where you
don't have רשות הרבים, everybody agrees צורת הפתח tzurat ha-petach is enough.
The גמרא Gemara moved from that from a case where you don't
even need it when it enters into a backyard with walls even
if the other end is open into the רשות הרבים. And the
גמרא concluded that that could be that that's fine, and the reason
why in an analogous case it was not good for the מבוי
was because of the issue of whether the people of the מבוי
joined in together with an עירוב with the people of the חצר.
Okay? Okay, דף יב עמוד ב daf yud beis amud beis at
the
top. We now move to the case of the מבוי where there
are three walls. We've dealt with the issue that it's open on
both sides, and now we move to what's the law if it
has three walls and one side's open. The גמרא says, איתמר, it
was stated, מבוי העשוי כנדלי. mavoi ha'asui k'nadli. רב says there is
no need for anything on the fourth side. And שמואל says you
need a לחי or a קורה korah. on the fourth side. Let's
see why they have this מחלוקת. machlokes. Okay, so let's draw this.
Let's explain what this case is. Okay, so נדלי nadli is a
word meaning a centipede and basically it's like a rectangular shape. So
you have a מבוי that's three walls. Okay, and the question is
whether the fourth side needs a לחי or a קורה. רב says
it doesn't and שמואל says it does.